# 大家好 今天來到了兄弟家的養蜂場看一下他的蜂蜜
Hi everyone! Today we come to our buddy's apiary and have a look at his honey,
# 蜜蜂
I mean honey bees.
# 你看 這裡很多哦
Look! Here's a lot!
# 你看
Look!
# 養蜜蜂也是挺辛苦的哦 就住在這個地方
Beekeeping is a rather tough work. He can just live in such a place,
# 棚子
a shed
# 媒氣灶
Gas stove
# 茶
Tea
# 開水
Boiled water
# 還有這個
And this one,
# 半夜睡在這裡 會不會怕
sleeping here in the midnight, won't you feel scared?
# 會不會有野豬來
Will there be any wild boars?
# 只能睡個棚子 沒辦法
He can only sleep in such a shed. Well,
# 都是為了生活
everything is for a living.
# 就是 地
It's just, the ground.
# 萬一下雨了怎麼辦
What would happen if it rains?
# 沒事
Nothing.
# 下大雨的時候
When it rains heavily?
# 那裡有水溝
There's a water pit.
# 哦
I see.
# 搭了這個棚就是為了那個 看 看 看這個蜜蜂
The shed allows him to, you know, to look, look, look after the, I mean, the bees.
# 你看的話又不行
You must take care of them you know.
# 所以天天在這在這裡
So he has no choice but staying here every day,
# 一年四季
all over the year,
# 春夏秋冬 嘖
summer and winder, gosh!
# 拿個帽子 那蜜蜂老是
I'll take a hat. The bees always,
# 老喜歡粘在我頭上
always like to fly onto my head.
# 這個我就不怕它啦 有了這個
Now they can't bother me anymore, with his hat.
# 誒呦 真的是哦
Eyo! It really works!
# 這就鑽不進啦
Now they can't get in.
# 你怎麼知道多還是少
How do you know whether there's a lot or not?
# 我打柱子的時候 抱了 很重(註︰不明白)
I was holding it in my arms. It was really heavy.
# 好厚就是很重
The thickness tells the weight.
# 哎呀
Aiya!
# 戴了這個
With the,
# 載了這個面罩 我就不怕啦
with the mask, I'm no longer afraid of them.
# 這個蜜蜂有點冬眠期
The bees are now entering the period of hibernation.
# 它要再[SIC]這裡躲著
They need to be hiding here.
# 你看一下我的蜜蜂 很多
Have a look at my bees.
So many!
# 那麼多蜜蜂的
There are so many bees.
# 這個有糖的 我知道 這個很重
There's honey in this frame. I know, it's really heavy.
# 哎呀
Aiya!
# 這個是有糖的 這個才是蜂[SIC]蓋蜜
There's honey. This is authentic comb honey.
# 哇
Wa!
# 好多糖啊 這個
There's so much honey!
# 你看 這都把它蓋子封起來就全是
Look! Sealed inside the comb, it's all,
# 全是那個蜜糖
all honey.
# 這個是蜜糖
This is honey.
# 不要浪費了 我來
Don't waste it. Let me take care of it.
# 誒呦
Eyo?
# 這邊這邊
This side, this side.
# 哦
Oh.
# 搞到手上了
It gets onto my arm.
# 哇
Wa!
# 很香啊 這個
It smells really good!
# 冬糖跟夏糖有甚麼區別
What's the difference between the honey in winter and summer.
# 冬蜜比較少
There's not so much honey in winter,
# 很少
just a little.
# 春蜜比較多
But there's more in spring.
# 哦
Oh!
# 那個 冬天的糖
You know, the honey in winter,
# 濃度也更 更高
has a much, much higher concentration.
# 哦
I see.
# 春天的水分比較多一點
And the honey in spring is a bit more watery.
# 怪不得
No wonder
# 它農度沒有那麼高
The concentration is not that high.
# 全部是封蓋了哦
It's all sealed, isn't it?
# 誒呦
Eyo?
# 這就有點糖
Here's a bit honey.
# 不要怕它蜇 手不會蜇的
Don't be scared. They don't sting on hands.
# 嗯 差點掉了
Um! I almost dropped it.
# 好香啊 哦
It smells really good, oh.
# 那種香味
The aroma...
# 四餅 四餅都好多糖哦
Four frames. All with, a lot of honey, right?
# 這個 這個蜂蠟 這個蜂臘能不能吃的
The, the beeswax, is the beeswax edible?
# 蜂蠟能吃滴 沒有糖
Beeswax is edible. But there's no honey.
# 有一點
There's a bit.
# 哇 這個
Wa! There's
# 這個就很多糖 嗯
there's a lot of honey.
Um.
# 這個糖要留給它過冬的
It's for the bees for the winter.
# 哦
Oh
# 這個下面是那個
Underneath are the, you know,
# 蜂蛹
the pupae,
# 蜜蜂仔
and larvae.
# 這裡的是糖
And here is the honey.
# 這個糖要留給它蜜蜂過冬
The honey is left for the bees for the winter.
# 冬天吃的 哪裡有仔
It's their food winter the winter.
Where are the larvae?
# 哦 我看到了 這邊是蜂仔
Oh! I can see them now. The larvae are on this side.
# 我 我看到了
I, I can see them now.
# 不一樣的子脾
The combs look different.
# 這個 它這是蜜脾 蜂蓋的蜜
These are for storing honey. They're sealed.
# 它這個是子啊 蜜蜂子
And these are for keeping larvae, larvae of bees.
# 蜂王比較一個 看一下在不在這裡
The queen is larger. Let's see if it's here.
# 可以 你看 這坨全是
Sure. Look! It's all here.
# 你點的時候不是那麼快 慢慢地點過去 然後慢慢地拿回來
Don't move too fast when you're getting the honey. Get your finger in slowly and get it back also slowly.
# 你這樣很快的拿回來它就會蜇你
You're moving too fast. They're gonna sting you.
# 好像有隻鑽進來啦
A bee seems to have got in.
# 誒 沒有
Eh? No.
# 你看 今天我都不怕它們了
Look! I'm not afraid of them anymore today!
# 吃多了蜜蜂
Now I've eaten a lot of honey bees,
# 哦不 吃多了蜂蜜
Ar no, I mean honey.
# 你看 它們都不蜇我了
Look! They're not stinging me anymore.
# 好 現在還有一點糖
Good! There's still a little bit honey,
# 也不是很多了
but not too much.
# 上次剛甩過
It has just been ripped.
# 留給蜜蜂吃啦 過冬
It's for the bees, for the winter.
# 這還有一點點 給留蜜蜂吃了
There's still a tiny little bit, for the bees.
# 不能再去甩了 甩了等下蜜蜂過不了冬
We can't rip it anymore. Otherwise, the bees would have no food for the winter.
# 這裡有多少箱
How many boxes are there?
# 兩三百箱
Two to three hundred
# 這裡兩三百窩
There are two to three hundred boxes here.
# 兩三百箱啊
Two to three hundred
# 我里面還有個蜂場
I have another apiary inside.
# 我家山上還有一個蜂場
I have another apiary in the mountain.
# 裡面還有
There're more inside.
# 數都數不出來 還有一個 那個蜂場
Uncountably many
There's still an, an apiary.
# 看一下 來 看一下
Let's take a look. Let's go!
Let's take a look.
# 這里 全是 每個箱都有的
Here, all boxes, every single box is filled with bees.
# 有 沒有空箱
Yea. No box is idle.
# 蜜蜂有幾 幾 幾個億哦 那個蜜蜂
You have hun, hun, hundreds of millions of, I mean, bees here, right?
# 你看 這裡有一條小溪哦 好山好水
Look! Here's even a stream. Wonderful environment!
# 啊 洗一下手 等下蜜蜂老是喜歡
Ah! Let me wash my hands. The bees are always,
# 在我手上鑽來鑽去
flying here and there between my hands.
# 不知道有沒有魚 這條小溪 應該有
Are there fish in this stream? There should be.
# 那麼乾淨 你看 這個水
It's so clean. Have a look at the water.
# 直接可以喝的哦
I can even drink it right away.
# 喝不到 不喝了
Not now. Forget it.
# 給套在這裡
It's covering my face.
# 那麼多
So many!
# 這密密麻麻的 全部是
Everything you see here, everything.
# 我們去看一下兄弟家割下來那個蜂蜜 (註︰他說割下來，那我唯有也譯割下來吧)
We're now going to have a look at the honey that my buddy has just harvested.
# 看一下 看一下有多少 現在還有多少
Let's see, let's see how much you have, how much you now still have.
# 大概兩三百斤的樣子吧
It seems to be around a hundred or a hundred and fifty kilograms.
# 那麼少 沒多少啦
So little
Not much left
# 今年 旱了一點 沒有多少
This year, it's a bit dry. So we don't have too much.
# 乾旱哦 嗯
Yea it's dry.
Um!
# 你看 這個就 冬蜜來的 很稠的哦 這個
Look! This is winter honey. It's really thick.
# 這個蜜 快結晶啦 你看 好多那個結晶體啦
The honey, is about to crystallize. Look! There are a lot of crystals.
# 馬上就變成白色的那個結晶
It's about to become the white crystals.
# 濃度好高哦 這個
It has really high concentration.
# 是啊
Indeed!
# 那麼多蜂 產量就那麼一點點
With so many bees, but the yield is just a tiny little bit here.
# 嗯 今年比較旱 很少這個蜜
Um! It's rather dry this year. So there's not so much honey.
# 冬蜜比較少的
Winter honey is relatively less,
# 濃度特高 濃度很高的哦
with exceptionally high concentration.
Yeah, the concentration is high.
# 馬上就會結晶的了
It crystallizes right away.
# 馬上就結晶啦
Yea, it crystallizes right away.
# 天氣冷它就把它結成一塊一塊的了
It's cold so the honey becomes crystals.
# 好香啊 整個桶都香的
It smells so good. The whole bucket smells wonderful.
# 這個很重的哦 剛好我們
It's really heavy. We've just tried,
# 抬都抬不動
but we couldn't move it a bit.
# 我還帶了個勺子
I even come with a spoon.
# 搞點吃一下 啊呀
Let me get some and have a try. Oya!
# 哇
Wa!
# 好好吃啊
Delicious!
# 它這個很濃哦 這個很稠了
It's really rich, and thick.
# 春天的就沒那麼稠
The honey in spring is not that thick.
# 沒嘗出味道來
I couldn't taste it well.
# 再來一點
Take a bit more.
# 真的很不錯耶 這種蜂蜜
It's really not bad, this honey.
# 吃到嘴巴裡面去都很香的
The aroma is so significant even when it's in the mouth.
# 你看 這個都是 像絲一樣的
Look! It's like, as smooth as silk.
# 你看 兄弟家還獲獎了哦
Look! These are my buddy's awards.
# 兩個都是銀獎
Both are silver awards.
# 你看 全南縣 土蜂場 百花蜜
Look! Quannan County. Chinese bees apiary. Multi flora honey.
# 中蜂 中蜂就是我們這邊的土蜜蜂
Chinese bees, Chinese bees are the local bees here.
# 中國的土蜜蜂
Local bees in China
# 你看 這個也是
Look! This award too.
# 百花蜜
Multi flora honey
# 也是中蜂 就是
It's Chinese bees again. That means,
# 我兄弟家養的全是那個
my buddy's bees are all the, you know,
# 土蜂蜜 (註︰他又搞錯蜂蜜和蜜蜂了) 就是中國的那個小蜜蜂
local honey bees, which are the local little bees in China.
# 所以質量比較好
So the quality is high.
# 叫兄弟搞兩瓶 帶回去
I ask my buddy to give me two jars, to bring back home,
# 給我家人吃一下
for my family.
# 剛好 差不多
Alright. It's enough.
# 不要裝那麼滿
Don't overflow it.
# 嘿呀
Heya!
# 太浪費了
It's too much a waste.
# 這裡就一斤左右哦
It's about 500 grams here.
# 蓋起來
Cover it up.
# 誒呦 可以 一蓋 可以
Eyo! Alright. Got it. Alright.
# 這樣就兩斤
Then it's one kilogram here.
# 等下放 放一個禮拜左右它就全部會結晶
Leave it, leave it for about a week and it will all crystallize.
# 結成那個 白白的晶體一樣的
It will become, like, the snowy white crystals.
# 現在都很 很稠啦 馬上就會結晶啦
It's really, really thick now. It will crystallize right away.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 今天的視頻就到這裡啦 先回去啦
The video ends here. Let's go back now.
# 誒呀
Eya!
# 你看 上次在兄弟家拿回來的這個冬蜜呀
Look! This is the honey that I've taken from my buddy.
# 才拿回來三四天就慢慢地開始結晶啦 你看
It started crystallizing in just three of four days. Look!
# 裡面都硬掉了 誒呦 彈手
It's already hard inside. Eyo! It hits my finger.
# 哇
Wa!
# 好稠哦 你看
It's really thick. Look!
# 都已經結塊了
It has already become crystals.
# 他這冬蜜
This is winter honey.
# 嘗一下
Let me try.
# 上次老弟偷吃了
My brother has stolen some last time.
# 好有味道哦
It's really flavourful.
# 你看
Look!
# 馬上就結 結成塊了
It be, becomes crystals right away.
# 要放置在瓶子裡面
It needs to be kept inside the jar.
# 你看 這個
Look! This is...
# 再過幾天的話就變成那個白白的 那個結晶
In a few days, it will become, you know, the snowy white crystals.
# 但產量太少啦
But the yield is too low.
# 這樣你看 這個
It's like, look!
# 像豬油一樣
It's just like lard.
# 這種蜂蜜我們再放幾天
The honey, let's leave it for a few more days.
# 我把它藏起來
I'll hide it well.
# 這個蓋子 很先進的哦
This lid, is advanced technology.
# 扣住它就行啦
Hook it here, and it's done.
# 啊 你看
Ah! Look!
# 就這樣子的
That's it!